<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short answer to a malicious pamphlet called, A reply written by John Gadbury, the King of England's juggler, and astrologer in ordinary to the Pope, to help on the work.</title>
            <author>Partridge, John, 1644-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39538</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18426696</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18426696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60055)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1643:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short answer to a malicious pamphlet called, A reply written by John Gadbury, the King of England's juggler, and astrologer in ordinary to the Pope, to help on the work.</title>
                  <author>Partridge, John, 1644-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>168-]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Partridge by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gadbury, John, 1627-1704. --  Reply to that treacherous and blasphemous almanack for 1687.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Astrology.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:107620:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107620:1"/>
            <head>A Short ANSWER TO A Malicious Pamphlet, called, <hi>A Reply;</hi> Written by JOHN GADBURY, the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Juggler, and Aſtrologer in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to the <hi>Pope,</hi> to help on the work.</head>
            <p>THis <hi>Gadbury</hi> being a new Convert to Popery, hath to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration armed himſelf with a vaſt Stock of <hi>Impudence</hi> and <hi>Villany;</hi> and theſe being joined to <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Lying,</hi> makes the Fellow the more <hi>Eminent</hi> and <hi>Notorious:</hi> as if theſe qualifications were inherent principles to his new Religion. And now he appears barefaced in defending Popery, pretending to write a <hi>Reply</hi> by way of Anſwer to an Almanack for the Year 1687, deſignedly writ to ridicule and oppoſe that <hi>Lying Religion.</hi> And this <hi>Reply</hi> of his is nothing elſe but a bundle of <hi>lies</hi> and <hi>forgeries,</hi> to abuſe the <hi>Author</hi> of that <hi>Almanack</hi> without the leaſt ground imaginable, to give <hi>Popery</hi> a Recommendation to the World, and to vindicate the <hi>villanous Agents</hi> in the preſent deſign of Subverting the <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> And in this Anſwer, I ſhall omit the taking notice of the major part of his Nonſenſe and Lies, as being not worth my pains, nor the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders time to examine; and imploy theſe few Pages to examine and refute thoſe things that are more remarkable, the reſt being eaſie and obvious to every impartial man: and in the firſt place, I will give you a <hi>Character</hi> of the <hi>Fellow,</hi> that you may thence gueſs at his Credit in every thing elſe that he pretends like a <hi>Champion</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, <hi>Ex pede Hercules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, This <hi>Fellow</hi> was by his Father brought up in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Church of England</hi> while he was young; and in this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107620:2"/>he continued for ſome years: but after he came to <hi>London [as he tells us in his Doctrine of Nativities]</hi> he ſhook off that, and went among the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> Congregations, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them ſo long, that he ſays [in that Book] they made him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt mad by preaching up the Doctrine of <hi>Free Grace.</hi> So that he then began to think of inquiring after a new Religion.</p>
            <p>And the firſt that he pitcht upon, and beſt pleaſed his vicious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, was that prophane Perſuaſion called <hi>Ramters, Familiſts,</hi> or <hi>ſweet Singers of Iſrael,</hi> a ſort of <hi>profuſe debauched Atheiſts,</hi> at that time very numerous: and to this he was Converted [or as the Cant then was, <hi>Begotten in the Faith</hi>] by <hi>Abiezer Cope,</hi> whoſe Piety and Reverence to a Deity may be gueſt at by this Expreſſion of his, who when he was committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> by the <hi>Parliament</hi> for ſpreading his damnable Hereſie, and being brought to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon door, he ſet his Arms on kembo, and ſaid, <hi>Be thou opened thou Everlaſting doors, and let the King of Glory come in.</hi> And by the way, as he was carried to Priſon, our <hi>Juggler</hi> hung on his <hi>Coach-ſide</hi> to beg his <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> calling him <hi>Father;</hi> and in this pious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion <hi>Jack</hi> grew in a ſhort time ſo good a Proficient, that at <hi>London-wall</hi> [being more than half drunk] he undertook to preach, his Text being theſe Words, <hi>And</hi> Jephthah <hi>was the Son of a Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot,</hi> Judges xi. ver. 1.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Religion,</hi> after ſome time, grew out of <hi>Faſhion</hi> with our <hi>Juggler,</hi> and then he was again upon the hunt for a new one: and as it happened, <hi>Cromwel</hi> had then taken upon him the Government, and <hi>Jack</hi> began to think of learning the <hi>Art of Whineing,</hi> that he might <hi>Cant</hi> at <hi>Whitehall;</hi> for he is certainly [as all <hi>Sycophants</hi> are] always, and in all times, of the <hi>Government ſide,</hi> be it never ſo <hi>baſe</hi> and <hi>lawleſs.</hi> And to this end he began to ingratiate himſelf there, and make friends to <hi>Cromwel</hi> that he might be permitted to dedicate his Doctrine of Nativities to him; but in this he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented to his great grief: and I am credibly informed, that he had promiſed all that a baſe Fellow could to be a Creature in that Government to the beſt of his power, but was not accepted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwel</hi> being dead, and the King likely to return, he then began to ſet up for a Church of <hi>England</hi>-man and Loyalty, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of his hard uſage in the time of Rebellion; and then it was <hi>Charles the Martyr</hi> at every word. In this Courſe and Cant he went on for ſome years, railing at the Rebels in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as now he doth at the <hi>Church of England in defence of Popery;</hi> till he was taken notice of by the men then in Power. In the Year 1666, he removed to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and turned a <hi>Whitehall Broker,</hi> which in plain terms is a <hi>Pimp;</hi> in which Profeſſion he did mighty well. And having
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107620:2"/>uſed the Trade a few Years, and found the <hi>Inclination of the Court,</hi> he began to <hi>abuſe Parliaments</hi> among thoſe he durſt truſt [of whom I was one, we then being intimate,] to cry up the <hi>Kings Abſolute Power,</hi> and ridicule all and every thing that was againſt <hi>Popery;</hi> which indeed at that time was a great Argument to me, that <hi>Popery</hi> was growing upon us; for I then thought he ſpoke the <hi>true Language of Whitehal.</hi> And now the Fellow began to grow intimate with Popiſh Prieſts, in whoſe Company I have been with him, he then hoping to make me as very a R — as himſelf; to accompliſh which, and bring me off from my Principles, he would often tell me that Religlon was nothing elſe but a <hi>Cheat,</hi> a <hi>Bugbear,</hi> and a meer <hi>trick of State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the Year 1677, and forwards, he then being intimate with that worthy Matron Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> Midwife to the Popiſh Plot, and his Kinſwoman, whoſe Narrative he afterwards writ; ſhe came to him to ask an Aſtrological Queſtion, and that was, Whether <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was fit to be truſted or not? Truſted, to do what? to Kill the King. No, No, but to know whether <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was fit to be truſted to get in her Husbands Debts, who was a Bankrupt, and had never a penny owing to him. But this was the ſham Queſtion that ſhe told the Council, to excuſe her ſelf.] So <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was truſted, and his buſineſs was to Kill the King; and this by <hi>Gadbury</hi>'s direction, as you may ſee at large in <hi>Danger-fields</hi> Depoſitions.</p>
            <p>In 1679. our Squire was for that committed to the Gate houſe, where he uſed, in my hearing, to rail often againſt his Cozen <hi>Cellier,</hi> calling her <hi>Whore</hi> and <hi>Bitch,</hi> and ſaid, ſhe had ruined him, and had undoubtedly been hanged if he had come to his Tryal; which to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, he ſent a large Bribe to Sir <hi>T. D.</hi> to deſire him to procure his Pardon. But that <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s honeſty and integrity was above Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery; and beſides he knew [by what he had confeſt before the Council] too much of his Villany to be concerned in his Pardon, and ſo refuſed. Then he ſent 100 Guinea's to the late <hi>Lord Angle-ſay</hi> to beg the ſame thing of him, to which his <hi>Lordſhip conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended;</hi> and by his Endeavour his Pardon was paſt, and he pleaded it in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> the <hi>Hillary Term</hi> following, and ſo eſcaped hanging at that time; and when he came out of Priſon he was by the Papiſts preſented with 200 pound for his faithful Service in the Cauſe, becauſe he had confeſt ſo little of the deſign. Now pray conſider, What <hi>Proteſtant Prince</hi> or <hi>Princeſs</hi> can be ſafe in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> while this Fellow remains unbaniſhed or unhanged; for he that did confederate with <hi>Popiſh Villains</hi> like himſelf to murder <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second, for no other reaſon but becauſe they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107620:3"/>
               <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> him to be a <hi>Proteſtant;</hi> will undoubtedly do it to thoſe that he is ſure are ſo, and make leſs ſcruple of it too, becauſe it is to ſerve the holy Cauſe in their hopeleſs condition.</p>
            <p>In 1685 on <hi>Sept.</hi> 9. two Romaniſts and my ſelf being at his houſe, he ſhewed us a <hi>Popiſh Biſhops Picture,</hi> and ſaid, that now the <hi>true Religion</hi> was coming in again, it was no crime to ſhew an <hi>honeſt mans</hi> picture; with divers ſuch Expreſſions, that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably ſufficient to prove him a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> for if <hi>Popery</hi> were the true Religion, he was a <hi>grand fool</hi> if he were not of it, if he did intend to be ſaved: but beſides this, he hath in divers of his late Scriblings, and eſpecially his <hi>Reply,</hi> given many good Reaſons ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to prove him a declared <hi>Papiſt.</hi> So that this is the fourth time he hath found it convenient to change his opinion: and the fifth time he Renegado-like hath changed his <hi>Religion,</hi> as if he made a Trade of it. So that now he is reduced to the principles of his original Spawn, his <hi>Mother</hi> being a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> of whom I could tell you a <hi>pleaſant Story,</hi> to ſhew that he ſtill retains the principles of her inſatiate luſt. However, the <hi>Papists</hi> have the honor to ſee this <hi>worthy member</hi> added to their Church, he that is as great a blemiſh to the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> as <hi>Sam. Parker</hi> is, and both of them a ſcandal to any but that of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould firſt come to anſwer his <hi>Popiſh Objections</hi> and <hi>lying Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertations</hi> in the Months, but that they are ſo notorious and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that whoſoever reads will gueſs at the man, and his meanings; for he is to <hi>oppoſe</hi> all that I have <hi>writ,</hi> and give it the <hi>Lye,</hi> that he may the better incourage the <hi>fooliſh Papiſts,</hi> and others converted in the great work, that the <hi>Gentleman</hi> you wot of will not <hi>dye in October next,</hi> that is, in 1688. for on his <hi>life or death</hi> depends the whole Affair; and for all his noiſe he now makes, he will tell you a year hence, about the time he is to <hi>change</hi> his <hi>Religion</hi> again, that he knew it too, but would not ſpeak of it.</p>
            <p>He ridicules and denies the Hurrycane at <hi>Whitehall</hi> in <hi>March</hi> and <hi>April</hi> laſt, when there was ſuch a turning out of the Court Officers almoſt to Admiration. He denies <hi>Ireland</hi> to be in diſtreſs, as I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned it in the Month of <hi>May:</hi> he quarrels with and denies the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of the <hi>Turk,</hi> which I predicted in <hi>July:</hi> he denies the quarrel and difference at <hi>Rome,</hi> which I predicted in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> which was the time that the <hi>Quietiſts</hi> made the firſt noiſe, and the <hi>Cardinals beard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Pope</hi> about it. He alſo denies the preferment of a <hi>Right-lined Clergy-man</hi> in <hi>October,</hi> which I predicted; but he forgets the <hi>Popiſh</hi> B. of <hi>Cheſter</hi> being ſent to <hi>Oxford in Commiſſion</hi> at that time. In <hi>December</hi> I predicted Perſecution; but he ſays there neither was nor could be any ſuch thing: I wonder what he calls turning out ſo many <hi>brave learned men at Magdalen College,</hi> and forbidding them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107620:3"/>to Exerciſe all and every part of the <hi>Miniſterial Function,</hi> or to be <hi>Tutors, Schoolmaſters,</hi> &amp;c. and all becauſe they would not <hi>perjure</hi> themſelves and turn <hi>Papiſts;</hi> is not this perſecution? No, no; <hi>'tis Popiſh Mercy</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is but a ſhort Anſwer to his <hi>twelve months,</hi> which I beg him to accept, and promiſe to give him a <hi>Longer</hi> as ſoon as I come to <hi>England.</hi> Some of the ſame that Collonel <hi>Manſel</hi> gave him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="refutation">
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> Chronology <hi>aſſerted, and the</hi> Lying Juggler <hi>refuted in all his Objections,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. <hi>Since</hi> Phocas <hi>Murdered his Maſter.</hi>— Here the <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> begins with a flouriſh, and makes an offer as if he intended to Huff us into ſubmiſſion: and calls in <hi>Platina</hi> and <hi>Heylyn</hi> for his Authors. As if by asking whether I had ever ſeen them, were Authority enough for the people to rely on what he ſays. But I will take the pains to examin him, and in doing that, I will prove him a Lyar.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he tells us, that <hi>Phocas</hi> did not make <hi>Boniface</hi> Pope, but found him ſo: Secondly, that the Title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop,</hi> was given to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of <hi>Marcian</hi> the Emperor, by the Council of <hi>Chalcedon.</hi> And thirdly, that <hi>Phocas</hi> did not give, but juſtly preſerved the Title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop</hi> to the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> Which are all three <hi>notorious Lyes,</hi> as you ſhall quickly ſee.</p>
            <p>This firſt is falſe, becauſe <hi>Phocas</hi> did not find <hi>Boniface</hi> Biſhop, but <hi>Boniface</hi> found <hi>Phocas</hi> Emperor: for when <hi>Phocas</hi> had by his Murder got the Empire, <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great ſate in the Epiſcopal Chair, after whom ſucceeded <hi>Sabinianus,</hi> and <hi>Boniface</hi> ſucceeded him, ſo that <hi>Boniface</hi> came to be Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> [not Pope, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that] about the fifth year of <hi>Phocas,</hi> as you may ſee by <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicus:</hi> ſo that <hi>Phocas</hi> was Emperor before <hi>Boniface</hi> was Biſhop.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is falſe: becauſe the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> gave the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> no Power nor Title but that of <hi>Primacy:</hi> and by vertue of that he was to take place of the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and all other Biſhops in publick and private Affairs, but no Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Title. And if the Juggler pleaſeth to obſerve, <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> had been nibbling at this Univerſal Title before, in which caſe <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great declared that it was <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and that whoſoever aſſumed that Title, was the fore-runner of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> So that you ſee this <hi>ignorant fellon</hi> knows not how to diſtinguiſh between a <hi>Primacy</hi> of Order and a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction;</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107620:4"/>between the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> being acknowledged for the firſt Biſhop, and his claiming to be Univerſal Biſhop over all Churches. The firſt was granted to the <hi>Roman</hi> See before, but this laſt, <hi>Boniface</hi> the third <hi>[alias Antichriſt]</hi> did firſt obtain of <hi>Phocas</hi> the Murderer.</p>
            <p>But for a further confirmation of this truth, I have here deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, let us ſee what <hi>Heylyn</hi> ſays, becauſe the <hi>Juggler</hi> hath made uſe of his name, and called him into his aſſiſtance. He likewiſe gives all thoſe before <hi>Boniface</hi> no other Title but Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> [pray mark that] and alſo makes <hi>Boniface</hi> the firſt of the Popes, of whoſe predeceſſor, <hi>Sabinianus,</hi> he ſays this, <hi>This is the laſt of the</hi> Roman <hi>Biſhops, not having that arrogant Title of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop or Head of the Church.</hi> By all which it is plain, that there was no ſuch Title as Univerſal Biſhop before <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, nor no Pope till <hi>Phocas</hi> made him ſo, by giving him that <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> arrogant Title.</p>
            <p>The third muſt naturally be falſe, becauſe it is deduced from the two falſe poſitions preceding. But here the <hi>Juggler</hi> doth, as all other <hi>Sycophants</hi> do, he gives villanous Actions, ſoft Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. He ſays, <hi>Phocas</hi> did not give, but juſtly preſerve the Title. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but I having ſpoke ſo largely before, it is needleſs to add more about that Point. Only take this ſhort account of <hi>Phocas,</hi> to ſhew that I had good reaſon to expreſs that Chronological Sentence, by the words which he reflects on, and cavils at.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Phocas</hi> was an Officer under the Emperor <hi>Mauritius,</hi> and having opportunity, he conſpired againſt his Maſter, and Murdered him, his Wife, and his five Children, and then by an Intereſt he made in the Army, was by them Proclaimed Emperor and finding his Friends few, and he like to be ſhaken, he Confederates with the then corrupt Clergy, and with that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Title he bought them to be his Creatures. So that by a bloody Murdering Emperor, that Antichriſtian Murdering Brood at <hi>Rome</hi> was ſet up: and they ſtill retain their Prophane Murdering Principles, which they Blaſphemouſly call Religion. And this is the Faith and Piety that <hi>John Gadbury</hi> endeavours to defend.</p>
            <p>Pag. 3. <hi>Of the Popiſh Powder Treaſon,</hi> &amp;c. — Here the Fellow draws a parallel between this Plot, and that which he calls <hi>Oates</hi>'s; thinking thereby to ridicule it. But as for <hi>Oates</hi>'s, we have now lived to ſee moſt part of what he ſwore prove true, and there can be no queſtion made of the truth of that in 1605. except by Papiſts, who would not have it believed, and he is one of thoſe. <hi>But his main Argument of Objection is, that it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107620:4"/>was a Popiſh Lord that diſcovered it, [Mount-Eagle] and therefore it cannot be true.</hi> The Fellow here makes a very bad Concluſion, for by his leave that objection ſignifies nothing to the truth or falſhood of it. But it ſhews, that all Papiſts are not equally wicked, and that there are ſome in whom Humanity and Moral Principles are too ſtrong for their Religion. Again he ſays, <hi>had the pretended deſign took effect, the Powder could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between Papiſts and Proteſtants:</hi> that is true; and for that reaſon they had no mind to Murder Papiſts with Proteſtants, which was the occaſion of writing the foreſaid Lettter: that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch warning that Lord might forbear coming to the Houſe, which ſome did, and were afterward queſtioned for it. But the word pretended ſhews you what Kidney the Fellow is of: and that he doth not believe it, and indeed he hath often told me that it was nothing elſe but a trick of King <hi>James,</hi> and the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans at that time, to Murder the Papiſts, which were for that end and purpoſe drawn in to Colour the thing. But when he ſpeaks of Sir <hi>George Wharton,</hi> that he ſings in Conſort with him, it is to tell you that he is a Papiſt, for Sir <hi>George</hi> dyed in that perſuaſion: thus you ſee what Cut Throat Villains our Juggler Defends and Juſtifies.</p>
            <p>Pag. 3. <hi>Of the Burning of</hi> London, <hi>and by whom,</hi> &amp;c. — Here honeſt <hi>Jack</hi> takes abundance of pains to excuſe the Papiſts, and after much ſhuffling, he concludes the Fanaticks Burned it: and the reaſon he gives was this, <hi>that the Papiſts would have ſhewed themſelves the moſt imprudent Men in the World, having their Riches and Relations there, if they ſhould do it;</hi> as if the Fanaticks had none there, which perhaps he may perſuade others to, yet knows the contrary himſelf. But pray obſerve, he calls all thoſe Fanaticks that were not declared Papiſts, <hi>and that they Burnt the City to anger the King and the Papiſts.</hi> Which if true they were really Fanaticks and mad Men, to burn about twelve thouſand of their own Houſes, and ruin their Families for no other reaſon but to anger the King and the Papiſts, as this Fool affirms, Ha, ha, ha. And again, rather than have it lye at the Papiſts doors [who were the real Authors of it] he Charges it upon God Almighty, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the Fanaticks and the Eaſt wind, being all of them Enemies to the King, the Papiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whence by his own words you may obſerve, that he makes <hi>two triple Parties,</hi> there is <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt wind,</hi> on the one ſide; and the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> on the other: now what do you think of this Fellow that brings his <hi>King</hi> in to be a <hi>Partner</hi> with the <hi>Devil,</hi> who is the great Patron and Father of the <hi>Lying Papiſts Faction,</hi> and the chief Agent for them in this and all other their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107620:5"/>Works of Darkneſs — well: but it muſt be the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> that burned it, why? Becauſe <hi>Lilly</hi> had ſaid it was a fit month for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns againſt the Government, and the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> were Enemies to it: ſo to aſſiſt them in the Affair, he brings God Almighty in as a Friend to them, and an Enemy to the King: and yet the Fool ſays it was burnt out of revenge: and he is ſo particular as to ſay it was for the blood of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt. Now were not theſe <hi>Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> wiſe fellows to burn their own Houſes, and ruin themſelves to revenge his death, and yet this done in ſpight to his Son? <hi>O you fool, lay your Lyes cloſer next time.</hi> — well: But it ſeems <hi>Noſtradamus</hi> Propheſied that it ſhould be Burned, and that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge too: and you in your <hi>Triggs</hi> Almanack [Mr. <hi>John</hi>] gave the beſt time for its Execution, as you confeſs your ſelf, and yet for all this we muſt not believe the Papiſts Burned it, nor that you had any hand in it.</p>
            <p>But for a cloſe of this Point, I refer the World to the <hi>Report</hi> of that Worthy Gentleman Sir <hi>Robert Brooks,</hi> Chairman to the Committee of <hi>Parliament,</hi> appointed to examin the Cauſe, and Authors of that dreadful Fire, which was Printed, where they will find by full Evidence, as clear as the Sun at noon day, by whoſe Order and Encouragement <hi>London</hi> was Burnt, and who rid up and down the City in the Fire-time with his <hi>Janizaries</hi> to Protect and defend the Fire Inſtruments, and got many of thoſe Men that were taken in the very Act, out of the hands of the Civil Officers, and conveyed them to <hi>Whitehal</hi> under pretence of ſecuring them in order to a Condign puniſhment, but inſtead thereof, they were gratified with pereſent Reward, and future Preferment. And that Honorable Gentleman, Sir <hi>Robert Brooks,</hi> for his fidelity to God and his Country, in diſcovery of that great Myſtery of Iniquity, was afterward by the Order and Contrivance of the ſame Party that cauſed <hi>London</hi> to be Burnt, Murdered in <hi>France.</hi> All which conſidered, I hope none can have the impudence to doubt who Burnt <hi>London,</hi> except the Authors and Actors in that curſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. And therefore the impudent Shuffles, Shams, and Excuſes of our Scribler <hi>Gadbury,</hi> to take it off from the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> muſt be a certain Argument to all thinking Men that <hi>they,</hi> and <hi>they only</hi> were the Actors and Contrivers thereof: which perhaps a little time may give more light to, and in the mean time I reſt ſatisfied of the truth of what I have here ſaid: and now what will you think of that fellow that turns Advocate for thoſe Miſcreants that Burnt your City, and alſo wait for an opportunity to Cut your Throats.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:107620:5"/>
Page 5. That the <hi>Papiſts Murdered</hi> 300000 Proteſtants in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> — Here <hi>Gadbury</hi> falls to his old way of quibling again, and gravely tells you, <hi>That it muſt be either lawful or unlawful; if the latter, all good men will bewail the Misfortune; but if the former, he would very fain know how men acting under a lawful Authority, and not going beyond their Commiſſion, can be guilty of Murder.</hi> So that at the firſt daſh the Fellow tells us, that they were <hi>Murdered by Order;</hi> and ſays, that it is not Murder if they do not go beyond their Commiſſion. Here he ſhews himſelf a right <hi>Saint of Rome,</hi> and a <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> for the <hi>Devil.</hi> The meaning of his words is no leſs than this: that if any <hi>Popiſh King</hi> ſhall give a Commiſſion to his <hi>Banditi, Jamſaries,</hi> or <hi>Murderers,</hi> to cut the Throats of all his <hi>Proteſtant Subjects;</hi> if they do not go beyond that Commiſſion, and cut the Throats of more than all, then it is no <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> Why? becauſe he tells you it is done by a <hi>Lawful Authority,</hi> and this calculated for the <hi>Meridian of England.</hi> So that you ſee he is not for denying the thing, nor the perſon; but juſtifies it to be Lawful, becauſe done by Commiſſion. And then asketh, how I will prove it? or whether I can ſhew any one of the Commiſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to this: There needs no other proof that the <hi>Maſſacre</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> was done by Authority than the <hi>late Kings</hi> Letter to the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Claims</hi> in behalf of the <hi>Lord Antrim</hi> the <hi>Chief Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in that <hi>horrid Murder.</hi> Where he tells them, that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>Lord</hi> had done nothing, but what was by the Order of his <hi>Father</hi> the <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> and his <hi>pious Queen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, when the charitable Collections were made in <hi>London</hi> and other parts for the relief of the diſtreſſed <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that had eſcaped the Murderers hands, and were ſent away in order to go for <hi>Dublin,</hi> they were all ſtopt at <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and there rotted and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed under the Wall of that City. Now by whoſe power this was done, I will leave to the Readers Judgment, and for its truth 'tis beyond all queſtion.</p>
            <p>Now Countrymen, is not this a good warning to <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to look to themſelves, ſeeing they are told by ſo notorious a <hi>Papiſt</hi> as <hi>John Gadbury</hi> is, that the cutting the Throats of 300000 <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> in purſuance of the <hi>Kings Commiſſion</hi> is not Murder?</p>
            <p>Page 6. Of the Murder of Sir <hi>Ed. Godfrey</hi> at Somerſethouſe— How now <hi>Jack:</hi> what! deny that Murder to be in <hi>Somerſethouſe:</hi> thou doſt act thy part as if thou hadſt been a <hi>Papiſt</hi> theſe 40 years: an abſolute Juggler! what, hath thy new Religion ſo ſuddenly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thee with its Maſter-piece of Impudence? Thou out-doſt all thy Wafer-Godmakers; for they perſwade us to believe but a little kind of a Cheat about Conjuring <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> into <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> by the vertue of <hi>hoc eſt corpus,</hi> that is <hi>Hocus Pocus:</hi> but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107620:6"/>thou doſt endeavour to out-face a Truth, that no man, but thoſe concerned in it, can have any cauſe to queſtion. The <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons, Judges, Juries,</hi> and all unconcern'd perſons, that have ever heard the Evidence, are aſſured of its truth beyond the leaſt doubt, But thou! armed with <hi>Pardon, Penſion, Guilt,</hi> and <hi>Impudence,</hi> doſt declare to the world, that thou wouldeſt be of any ſide for Mony. And for <hi>Prance</hi>'s pleading guilty to an <hi>Indictment of Perjury.</hi> I wonder you are not aſhamed to mention it: if you conſider that we know he was hired to do it: and that by the <hi>Prieſt</hi> at <hi>White-hall,</hi> &amp;c For I ſaw the Letter in his own hand that was ſent to him by the order of his Wife's two Brothers, both <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> and others of that Tribe; <hi>in Which they promiſed his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and that he ſhould again live like a Man, if he would come over, and tell the truth about that Murder</hi> (he then being at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi>) upon this he ſaid, <hi>That to tell the truth in their ſenſe, was to forſwear all he had ſwore before;</hi> and deſired <hi>Ged to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him, if all he had ſworn about</hi> Godfrey<hi>'s Murder were not true; and that if he ſhould ever deny it, he deſired us all that were then in Company,</hi> which were about five or ſix, <hi>to call him perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Rogue:</hi> and let him deny this if he can. Thus Reader you ſee what ſtreſs they lay on the Perjury of this poor deluded <hi>Raſcal.</hi> Yet neither he, nor this man, nor their <hi>Wafer-Godmakers</hi> themſelves, have hitherto been able to give better Anſwers and Arguments to deſprove it; <hi>but to ſay, they are mere Stories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the vizzanded Villains he ſpeaks of, one of them is well known, namely the then Queens Confeſſor, who there brandiſhed his Sword on the Scaffold for joy the King was beheaded.</p>
            <p>Page 7. Since that <hi>Pious Prince Charles</hi> the Second dyed a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and yet Head of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Here my Friend at the firſt daſh doth confeſs, that <hi>pious Prince</hi> did dye a <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,</hi> Really the old Gentleman is mightily obliged to him for his kindneſs, to tell it ſo impudently, that he lived a <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> and died an <hi>Idolater.</hi> For it is well known, he did communicate three times every year with the <hi>Church of England</hi> in the Sacrament. And yet by this Man he is affirmed to be a <hi>Roman Catholick.</hi> Now confider, if he was a <hi>Papiſt.</hi> Do you think he was not a precious pious Head of a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Body. and the <hi>Church of England</hi> in a fine condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be protected and defended from <hi>Popery</hi> by a Prince of that perſwaſion, and the Holy Sacrament of our Lord, is by the <hi>Lords An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed</hi> made a Decoy to cheat the People into the belief that he was a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> But my Adverſary ſays, that the Traytors plotted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, while he was not declared to be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and mentions the <hi>Rye-houſe.</hi> Truly <hi>Jack,</hi> if you did not know, or at leaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, he was a <hi>Papiſt</hi> then, you were a very ignorant Fellow; for it was was well known, that he was ſo at his firſt coming into <hi>England</hi> in the year 1660.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:107620:6"/>
And when he talks of the <hi>Rye-houſe Plot,</hi> he ſays, <hi>The King's precious Life was in danger.</hi> Why? was it more in danger at that time than when <hi>Jack Gadbury</hi> was in the <hi>Meal-Tub,</hi> ſcouring <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfields Kettle</hi> with Mrs. <hi>Celier,</hi> to prepare him for the Murder of that pious King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I think not; but beſides, the Fanaticks did but talk of killing him, but the <hi>Papiſts</hi> did it effectually.</p>
            <p>In the concluſion my Adverſary takes care that I may know what the <hi>Church of England</hi> is: and therefore directs me to a Treatiſe called <hi>Good Advice,</hi> &amp;c. written by <hi>William Pen</hi> the pretended <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> who is a <hi>Socinian,</hi> as appears by his <hi>Sandy Foundation ſhaken,</hi> where he downright denys the <hi>Trinity;</hi> and a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as all men may judg by his Promotion and Favour at <hi>White-hal</hi> at this time of day; ſo that I am like to be well informed of the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England</hi> by ſuch a Fellow as this is. And to be plain with you <hi>Jack,</hi> I doubt you are out in your Topick in this point, as well as in your Head of the Church. But I perceive by your pious Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> will make as good a Head of the Church as any of them all: and then too, I am ſure you will be on the Government ſide, if poſſible you can, you are ſo good a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 8. Since <hi>James</hi> the Second took the Coronation Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here the Fellow mounts the high Rope again, and tells us, that it is true, <hi>The King did take the Coronation Oath,</hi> but <hi>it was by his own free choice, and might have chuſed whether he would or not.</hi> But let me tell him, that this is a groſs Lye; for it is not Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Choice in the <hi>King</hi> to take it, but an <hi>Indiſpenſible</hi> duty: neither are the Subjects obliged to take the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> till he hath taken that. For as he ſwears to preſerve them in their Rights and Priviledges, ſo they ſwear to ſtand by him in the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Laws, ſo that the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and the <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> Oath are <hi>Reciprocal</hi> and <hi>Equally</hi> binding. And the <hi>King</hi> is defective in divers points of his Duty and Power till that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and done. And let me tell you Mr. <hi>Jack,</hi> the Subjects have a Right as well as the <hi>King,</hi> and both by the ſame Law. And if the <hi>King</hi> refuſeth to be a <hi>King</hi> by Law, there is neither reaſon nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for them to ſwear Obedience; for the Obedience due to him as <hi>King</hi> by Law, doth alſo oblige him by the ſame Law to protect them in their <hi>Lives, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Eſtates.</hi> So that it is unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable that the Law ſhould force the <hi>Subjects</hi> to ſwear to obey and maintain a <hi>Prince</hi> in his Right, and not <hi>compel him</hi> to give them aſſurance by Oath, that they ſhall enjoy theirs alſo. And if it were otherwiſe, it would ſhew great weakneſs in the <hi>Legiſlators</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to bind the one and leave the others to his Will, when the <hi>Government</hi> of both is by <hi>Compact.</hi> But I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107620:7"/>my Friend <hi>John</hi> builds his opinion on <hi>Filmore,</hi> ſuch another ſorry <hi>Sycophantizing Fellow</hi> as himſelf, who hath many flouriſhes and words, and but very little Law, and leſs Reaſon and Honeſty. However, he and <hi>Jack</hi> together would form a moſt admirable ſort of Government for a Kingdom or Nation to be governed by <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons,</hi> and converted by <hi>Booted Apoſtles:</hi> Thus you may ſee what a ſpecial Engliſhman our Friend is, and a hopeful Caſuiſt, that can guard and defend their tottering Cauſe with nothing but Lyes.</p>
            <p>Page 9. Since Judge <hi>Street</hi> — 00000000000 <hi>Treſilian—How now Jack:</hi> What are you turned Advocate for <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall?</hi> are thoſe Benches ſupply'd with ſuch <hi>Ignorant Fellows,</hi> that they muſt make uſe of a <hi>Scribler</hi> to defend them with Arguments of downright Impudence? This is a fine Credit for your <hi>Law</hi> and your <hi>King.</hi> Well <hi>Jack,</hi> you tell us of a <hi>Riddle,</hi> and that you have been the <hi>Oedipus</hi> to unfold it. And you ſay the eleven Cyphers with <hi>Treſilian</hi> at the end of them, ſhews that eleven of the twelve <hi>Judges</hi> muſt be hanged. Why really <hi>Jack,</hi> you are in the right; for that is the meaning of it; and it doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew the merit and fate of the Villains, but it is alſo a piece of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that will ſhortly be accompliſhed. But pray obſerve: When the <hi>Fellow</hi> hath unfolded the <hi>Riddle,</hi> and told them that <hi>hanging</hi> is their <hi>due;</hi> leſt they ſhould faint under the Conſideration of their deſtiny, and think themſelves into their <hi>Graves,</hi> and cozen <hi>Tyburn; He licks them up with ſome Oyl of Fool,</hi> and calls them <hi>Loyal Judges,</hi> and <hi>Reverend Sages;</hi> and then perks up with a ſtrain of his accuſtomed Impudence; and asketh <hi>what they have done? Done ye Slave!</hi> What have they not done to make themſelves <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Traytors,</hi> in all kind of Villany and Treaſon, that lyeth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Sphere of their power and action?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They have by their Suffrage given the <hi>King</hi> a power <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to Law,</hi> for which Crime <hi>Treſilian was hanged.</hi> For it is one thing to connive at the Non-execution of the Laws, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take away their <hi>Obligatory Force;</hi> one thing to ſupercede a Law, wherein his own benefit is concerned, and another to diſpence with Laws made for the <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and <hi>Subjects:</hi> and this they have done, in giving their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, that the <hi>King</hi> may diſpence with <hi>all Law,</hi> as he ſees good. You may remember <hi>Jack,</hi> that when <hi>Richard</hi> the Second had pick'd a pack of Judges for his purpoſe, ſuppoſe ſuch as theſe, or not quite ſo bad: and thoſe were <hi>Treſilian, Belknappe, Holt, Fulthorp, De Burgh, Lockton,</hi> and others: the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> the <hi>King</hi>'s Creature, with the reſt of his Conſorts, formed the then deſign in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>ten Queries,</hi> under the power of which (being granted) they intended to manage and carry on their curſed Plot; and on the 25. of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107620:7"/>
               <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the eleventh year of the King, in <hi>Nottingham Caſtle,</hi> the ſaid <hi>ten Queries</hi> were propounded to the foreſaid Judges, to which they all conſented: and when they had ſigned and ſealed according as they were deſired, <hi>Belknappe</hi> broke out into this Expreſſion, and ſaid: <hi>Now I want nothing but a Ship, a nimble Horſe, or an Halter, to bring me to the death I deſerve, for my Treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Nobles of the Land.</hi> Which <hi>ten Queries</hi> and the thirty four <hi>Articles of Treaſon,</hi> which they were after charged with, you may find Printed in the Life of <hi>Richard the Second,</hi> which are too long here to inſert. And when you have conſidered both their Crimes, you will ſay that the Judges under <hi>James the Second</hi> have outdone thoſe of <hi>Richard the Second,</hi> and yet this Man asketh what they have done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They have uſed their utmoſt endeavour to bring in <hi>Popery:</hi> they have not only connived at the baſe Actions, uſed to encourage the <hi>Popiſh Party</hi> in their preſent damnable deſigns, to overthrow the Government, and alter Religion; but have alſo given advice and direction for the doing of it, and viſibly ſhewed their Endeavour by encouraging baſe and unjuſt Proſecutions, Fining, Hanging, &amp;c. all thoſe that have ſtood in the way of it. And when any ſuch Cauſe came to be tryed where the Defendant was looked on as an <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>the Government</hi> (as they uſually call all thoſe that they are minded to ruin) they never uſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult <hi>Raſtal, Pulton</hi> or <hi>Keble,</hi> &amp;c. in the true Law that did relate to the merit of the Cauſe. But took their direction from the <hi>Lord Kings-will, Sir John doe-it,</hi> and <hi>Sir William 'Tis-well,</hi> all of them great <hi>Lawyers</hi> at <hi>White-hall.</hi> And is not the Defendant or Priſoner in a fine Condition in ſuch a Caſe as this? But that which leaves them without excuſe is, that they know the Laws which are made, and ſtill in force againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> againſt all thoſe that are reconciled to the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and thoſe that do but aſſiſt in any thing that concerns the promotion of the <hi>See of</hi> Rome <hi>in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly:</hi> They have not only ſhewed how willing they are to have <hi>Popery</hi> introduced; but alſo their readineſs to aſſiſt in that work, as may be ſeen by their Carriage at <hi>Oxford,</hi> where they may ſhortly hear of a <hi>piece of Burglary</hi> by them committed at <hi>Maudlin Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,</hi> and other kind of Violences without any pretence of Law, unleſs it were that of the Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſion, which at the beſt can be but an Abortive ſprung out of the ruins of <hi>Star Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Tyranny.</hi> Which was long ſince declared to be againſt Law, and an Oppreſſion to the Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly:</hi> In the Weſt in 1685 when the Priſoners were brought before them to be tryed, they compelled them to plead guilty right or wrong, or elſe they threatned to hang them up preſently: ſuch a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107620:8"/>piece of Barbarity that all the Hiſtories of <hi>England</hi> can give no pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of it; To hang men immediately, unleſs they would confeſs themſelves guilty of ſuch Crimes, that under the pretence of Law they might hang them a day or two afterward: and this divers perſons were forced to do that were innocent, and yet they were hanged for all that. So that after this method they deſtroyed more men in a fortnight or three weeks, than <hi>Treſilian,</hi> and all the reſt of thoſe kind of Rogues did in two hundred years before, without the leaſt remorſe or extenſion of the diſpenſing power this impertinent Fellow ſo <hi>idlely</hi> and ſo <hi>knaviſhly</hi> pleads for. By which I apprehend that he would have it allowed for no other end, but to protect and maintain ſuch <hi>Creatures</hi> as <hi>he</hi> and <hi>they</hi> are, that for Lucre and Malice will undertake any thing they are put upon, and then they are ſure to be ſafe in their Villany.</p>
            <p>But obſerve, my Friend <hi>John</hi> chargeth <hi>Treſilian</hi> with cruelty for inditing 2000. perſons at <hi>Coventry,</hi> which was indeed a great piece of Villany; but alas! that was nothing to theſe <hi>Judges;</hi> for he did but pick their pockets of a little Mony; but theſe Villains murdered the men, and pickt their pockets too: So that <hi>Jeffry's</hi> need not doubt but Hiſtory will record him for a famous Fellow, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe he hath out-done <hi>Treſilian.</hi> And yet this man <hi>Gadbury</hi> their <hi>Advocate</hi> asketh, <hi>with whom they have conſpired; what Countries they have injured; what ſingle perſon they have oppreſſed, and wherein they have given the Council of Treſilian;</hi> and then bids me <hi>ſpeak</hi> if I can. Now Sir, I have ſpoke, and ſo much truth too, that all your ſhams will never be able to gain-ſay to clear your villanous Clients.</p>
            <p>But the Fellow ſays, <hi>That they all moſt happily draw in a Yoke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the good of the King,</hi> and by the <hi>Grace of God</hi> they may all live to be <hi>drawn together, and yoked for the good of the Nation.</hi> And then they'll think him their beſt Friend that can ſeparate one or more of their necks from the <hi>Yoke;</hi> and alſo find the Effects of declaring a power in the <hi>King</hi> to diſpenſe with all Law; and a good pair of heels will be then of more ſervice to them than all the Arguments that can be raiſed to juſtifie their Treaſons, either by themſelves, the Popiſh Prieſts, or their great <hi>Advocate Jack Gadbury;</hi> and ſo I will preſent them with a New-years Gift.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>DIgnify'd things!</hi> may I your leave implore,</l>
               <l>To kiſs your hands, and your great Heads adore;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Judges</hi> you are, but you are <hi>ſomething more.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May I draw near; and with a rough hewd pen,</l>
               <l>Give a ſmall draught of you, the worſt of men:</l>
               <l>All of your merit, and your mighty skill,</l>
               <l>And how your <hi>Charms</hi> all <hi>Courts of Juſtice fill.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your Law's</hi> far ſtronger than the <hi>Common Votes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And finely flows through your <hi>diſpenſing Throats.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:107620:8"/>
What <hi>Rome</hi> will ask, you muſt her not deny;</l>
               <l>If <hi>Hell</hi> commands you too, you will <hi>comply:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There's none but you would in this Cauſe combine;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Things made like Men,</hi> but act like <hi>Bruits</hi> and <hi>Swine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Law-books are traſh: A Student, he's a Drudge:</l>
               <l>Learn to ſay <hi>yes;</hi> he's the <hi>accompliſht Judge:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He wins the <hi>Scarlet Robe;</hi> and wears it too:</l>
               <l>Ay, and deſerves it well, for <hi>more's his due;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All that <hi>compleats a Traytor,</hi> dwells in you.</l>
               <l>Thus you like Villains to the <hi>Benches</hi> get,</l>
               <l>And in defiance to the Law you ſit,</l>
               <l>And all <hi>baſe Actions,</hi> that will pleaſe, commit.</l>
               <l>There muſt you toil for <hi>Rome,</hi> and alſo try</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Iriſh Sence,</hi> and <hi>Cobweb Policy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Compleat your <hi>Crimes,</hi> and then you're fit to dye.</l>
               <l>True Loyal Babes, <hi>Pimps</hi> to the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Treſillians Heirs; Heirs</hi> to his <hi>Crimes</hi> and <hi>Doom.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was e'er that <hi>Hall</hi> fill'd up with ſuch a brood,</l>
               <l>All dipt in <hi>Treaſon, Villany,</hi> and <hi>Blood?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Worſe than <hi>Fanatick Prieſts,</hi> for they being preſt</l>
               <l>By a wiſe Prince preacht to <hi>Repeal</hi> the <hi>Teſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then here's the difference 'twixt your <hi>Popiſh</hi> Tools,</l>
               <l>You're <hi>downright Rogues,</hi> they only <hi>Knaves</hi> and <hi>Fools.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Deus dabit his quoque funem.</p>
            <p>Page the <hi>10th.</hi> Since the <hi>King</hi> could diſpenſe with the Teſt, &amp;c. Here my Adverſary makes a long Harangue about the diſpenſing power lodged in the <hi>King,</hi> which was never queſtioned as ever I heard; eſpecially in that part which concerns himſelf in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. For example: In the caſe of <hi>Murder,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> can par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Injury done to him in the loſs of a Subject; but he cannot wholly indemnifie the Malefactor from the rigor of the Law. As you may ſee in the Caſe of <hi>Appeal,</hi> which hath hanged thoſe that the <hi>King</hi> hath pardoned. So in the caſe of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> he can par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that part of it which is againſt Him; but all Treaſon is againſt the <hi>Subjects</hi> as well as the <hi>King:</hi> and by my Adverſaries leave, that is out of the King's power to pardon, tho e ſays many have expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced it, but I know none except Papiſts, Prieſts and Jeſuits; but for Proteſtants he can name few or none, and them that have, bought it with their penny as cheap as they could get it of ſome Miſs or other Favorite.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe this were granted, which he pleads for, what would he then make of it? doth that part of the Prerogative alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power the <hi>King</hi> to diſpenſe with thoſe Laws made by the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates for the ſecurity of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Religion? Certainly no.</hi> For
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107620:9"/>when the Conſent of the three Eſtates is paſſed into an Act, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry individual Man as a Subject is bound to keep and obey it, and the King to ſee it executed. And there is no Diſpenſing nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing that Act, but by the conſent of the three Eſtates that made it. And this the <hi>Papiſts</hi> well know, which makes them try ſo many tricks to pack a <hi>Parliament</hi> to have it done. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Judges have given their Opinions, that the <hi>King</hi> may diſpenſe with the <hi>Teſt</hi> and other Laws alſo in any Caſe where he thinks fit: Yet the <hi>Court,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and the more knowing ſort of Papiſts are not (you ſee) ſatisfied with that, but are ſtill uſing their utmoſt endeavours to have it done by a form of Law: from whence the Reader may obſerve two things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever takes any place of Truſt, &amp;c. contrary to the <hi>Teſt,</hi> are Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, notwithſtanding the Judges Opinions and the <hi>Kings</hi> Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: and this the Papiſts know full well. <hi>Secondly,</hi> that this diſpenſing power can laſt no longer than the <hi>King</hi> lives, and then thoſe that are offenders with the <hi>Judges,</hi> &amp;c. will hardly eſcape the <hi>Gallows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I wonder my Adverſary is ſo confident, as to ſay the <hi>Teſt</hi> was made to exclude the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>York</hi> from the <hi>Crown,</hi> when he was the only perſon therein excepted by name: but indeed it is no wonder if we conſider his Folly and Impudence in every thing elſe.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the <hi>Nole proſequi</hi> that he mentions: it is of the ſame nature wich his power to pardon, and both ought to be uſed only in particular Caſes of Neceſſity to ſave or relieve the Innocent, but not to make a common practice of either to protect known <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, Thieves, Murderers,</hi> and Papiſts from Juſtice: and ſo I have done with the <hi>Ridiculous Obligations, falſe Aſſertions,</hi> and <hi>imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Arguments</hi> about the <hi>Chronology,</hi> made of <hi>John Gadbury,</hi> the preſent <hi>Advocate</hi> for the <hi>baſe Actions</hi> and <hi>Treaſons</hi> of the Enemies of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to take notice of the reſt of his Malicious Stuff, which I find ſo Idle, that I ſhall paſs by moſt of it, and only take notice of ſome of the moſt abſurd things, to ſhew you how Malice and his new Religion hath tranſported the fellow, and made him forget to write truth.</p>
            <p>In Page the <hi>18th</hi> he tells us of the great plenty and abundance of Fruit and Herbage in the year 1687. <hi>When</hi> (ſays he) <hi>have we had a more peaceable calm and quiet year? when were we bleſt with greater plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of fruit and herbage?</hi> Now obſerve: for in the pag. next following the <hi>Summer Ingreſs</hi> in <hi>his Almanack</hi> for the year 1688. he ſays, <hi>We have had great Scarcity of Fruit and Herbage every year ſince the great froſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107620:9"/>in</hi> 1683/4, and particularly he ſays, <hi>that the two laſt years of</hi> 86 <hi>and</hi> 87, <hi>wheat yielded almoſt two thirds leſs than it uſed to do in other years.</hi> Now do you think that this man underſtands his own non-ſence himſelf? For firſt, he comes with a <hi>when were we bleſt with a greater plenty than in</hi> 1687? and then in his other Libel he ſays, <hi>When have we had more Scarcity than in the years</hi> 1686. <hi>and</hi> 1687? Thus you ſee what a kind of fellow I have to deal with; but <hi>Papiſts</hi> may ſay any thing at this time.</p>
            <p>He alſo calls it <hi>a peaceable and quiet year;</hi> but for my part I have not known the Nation in a greater Convulſion for many years than it was this laſt, and is ſtill. How many <hi>worthy Honeſt Gentlemen</hi> were turned out of the <hi>Commiſſion of Peace? Lord Lieutenants, Deputy Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Governours of Towns, Commanders,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Men of Honor</hi> turn'd out, and <hi>Scoundrils</hi> put in; <hi>Tory's</hi> turn'd out, and <hi>Whiggs</hi> put in; <hi>Whiggs</hi> put out, and <hi>Papists</hi> put in; <hi>Engliſh Gentlemen</hi> turn'd out, and <hi>Bogtrotters</hi> put in; <hi>Law deſtroyed, Religion invaded,</hi> the <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi> and <hi>Rules of Government turn'd up by the Roots;</hi> the <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Rights</hi> of <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities ſeized by force,</hi> and all to bring in <hi>Popery.</hi> And yet this Fellow calls it a <hi>peaceable quiet year.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then he Bluſters up again, and Asketh, <hi>when was</hi> Weſtminſter Hall <hi>leſs thronged in term time than now?</hi> Alas <hi>Jack!</hi> that is not from <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the 7th, as you fondly imagin: but the people are ſenſible, that the <hi>Judges</hi> who ſit there, are neither <hi>wiſe</hi> nor <hi>honeſt.</hi> And what wiſe man will put his <hi>Cauſe</hi> or <hi>Estate</hi> into the hands of <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Knaves</hi> if he can help it? for let a <hi>Papiſt</hi> be <hi>Plaintif,</hi> and an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to <hi>Popery</hi> the <hi>Defendant,</hi> you may know who will carry the Cauſe without ſetting a Figure. And this is the preſent Caſe of poor <hi>Ireland,</hi> which <hi>Gadbury</hi> ſays, is in a very good Condition. And perhaps ſo it may in his ſence, that is, to deſtroy the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 24 and 25, he makes a long impertinent ſtory in order to abuſe Commonwealths, and after he hath emptied himſelf of his fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſtuff, he comes in page 26. to give reaſons why Commonwealths are to be abhorred, and Monarchy preferred, <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>if God had intended a man ſhould have been in love with a Commonwealth, he would have created him with a head on each ſhoulder.</hi> A very learned Reaſon: and then by the ſame Rule, if God had intended the world ſhould have been governed by <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Lawleſs Monarchs,</hi> he would have ſent all <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> into the world with <hi>Boots</hi> and <hi>Spurs</hi> on, and all Subjects ſhould have been born with <hi>Saddles</hi> on their <hi>Backs,</hi> that they might have been rid without Controule, as their Riders had ſeen fit.</p>
            <p>A <hi>ſecond</hi> Reaſon is, If Government (like the body natural) ſhould have many Heads, it would be a Monſter: and would it not be the ſame if it had but one <hi>Head,</hi> and that a great deal too <hi>big</hi> for the <hi>body,</hi> or a very <hi>ugly</hi> one? for a ſingle Head may be a Monſter as well as <hi>two Heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:107620:10"/>
A <hi>third</hi> Reaſon is, <hi>becauſe there is one Sun, and but one Sun in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ergo, &amp;c.</hi> What the Fellow brings in this for to prove <hi>Monarchy,</hi> ſeems to me a <hi>Paradox;</hi> and eſpecially ſuch a <hi>King</hi> as he pleads for: which is to conſume his <hi>Subjects Wealth,</hi> to <hi>destroy</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> he is ſworn to maintain, and to <hi>bring</hi> in and <hi>impoſe</hi> what <hi>innovations</hi> in <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> He thinks fit, or rather what the <hi>Villanous Priests</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall perſwade him to that is moſt advantageous to their <hi>Cheating Trade</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of <hi>Religion.</hi> But the <hi>Sun</hi> is the univerſal body of Light, and like a ſteward in truſt doth <hi>diſperſe</hi> and <hi>diſpence</hi> it to all <hi>Stars,</hi> and to the World likewiſe, but doth receive from none: alſo the <hi>Sun</hi> preſerves the <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of Nature which <hi>God</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in the beginning, but deſtroys none. Laſtly, let him make the beſt of it, and the <hi>Sun</hi> is no more than a <hi>Stadtholder,</hi> or a <hi>King</hi> by <hi>Compact.</hi> For the <hi>Moon</hi> hath as great a ſhare in the <hi>Government</hi> of the World as he hath, and <hi>Saturn, Jupiter, Mars, Venus</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> as much as either of them, So that by his <hi>impertinent notion,</hi> there ought to be as many <hi>Kings</hi> as <hi>Planets</hi> in the <hi>Government</hi> of every <hi>Nation..</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is but one <hi>Sun,</hi> one <hi>Moon,</hi> one <hi>Saturn,</hi> one <hi>Jupiter.</hi> &amp;c. For each <hi>Planet</hi> hath his ſhare and power in the production of men and things; neither would the order of Nature be perfect, if either of them were wanting; for <hi>God made nothing in vain,</hi> But to tell you the truth of all, this is an <hi>Arbitrary Notion,</hi> which he learned of Sir <hi>George Wharton</hi> above thirty years ago: and therefore he might have told us here alſo, that he ſpoke in that <hi>Gentlemans Cant,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Powder Plot.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But one thing I cannot paſs by without taking notice of it. And that is, in Page 27. he tells us, <hi>that a Commonwealth is the Bramble of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion;</hi> alluding there to the Parable of <hi>Jotham</hi> on mount <hi>Gerizzim,</hi> about the Trees going forth to chooſe a <hi>King;</hi> and they choſe the <hi>Bramble</hi> for their <hi>King.</hi> Now you know it is the nature of a <hi>Bramble</hi> to ſcratch and tear all that it comes near (as <hi>Gadbury</hi> obſerves:) but the <hi>Bramble</hi> was not choſe for a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> but for a <hi>King.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how he will make this ſerve to ſet out the greatneſs of a <hi>King,</hi> I cannot tell, unleſs he hath made choice of this to abuſe and affront them; for I am ſure, it can be taken no otherwiſe: However, pitty his Folly and his Ignorance in this and every thing elſe, for if he knew bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he would do better; for when he calls the <hi>Bramble</hi> a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> he calls himſelf a <hi>Common Coxcomb.</hi> But it is no wonder in this Caſe, becauſe he is the ſame in every thing elſe. In his <hi>Astrology</hi> he is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Ignarant Fellow.</hi> And his ſcandalous Libel throughout is nothing elſe, but <hi>Cant</hi> and <hi>Noiſe.</hi> As you ſee in the <hi>Nativity,</hi> he there talks of which is all falſe; his <hi>Palladium</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> his <hi>Quotations</hi> out of <hi>Haly;</hi> his pretended <hi>Astrological Reaſons</hi> to prove the predictions in the Month falſe; in all which it is nothing elſe but <hi>Trick</hi> and <hi>Sham.</hi> But I do not much wonder he is got into this <hi>falſe Courſe</hi> and <hi>Custom,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:107620:10"/>when I conſider he is turned <hi>Papiſt,</hi> a <hi>Lying falſe Religion;</hi> and never was <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Proſelyte</hi> better matcht than now in <hi>Jack Gadbury</hi> and <hi>Popery.</hi> And this is the Courſe and Cuſtom he will live in till the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment altars in <hi>England;</hi> for when <hi>Popery</hi> goes out of faſhion, then he leaves it; and I ſuppoſe about twelve Months hence it will be <hi>Hey</hi> for a new <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Page 28. he ſays, <hi>There was never ſuch a civiliz'd Army in</hi> England <hi>as at this day:</hi> and he is ſure, <hi>no man hath been wronged of a Pig, Hen, or Egg, without Redreſs,</hi> &amp;c. Here let the whole Nation be Judges; For the behaviour of the Soldiers, and the Complaints of the People from all parts of the Nation, are viſible evidences of the Fellows Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence: But perhaps the <hi>Rapes, Robberies</hi> and <hi>Murders</hi> they commit, are nothing if they let the <hi>Pigs</hi> and the <hi>Hens</hi> alone; or perhaps he thinks the hanging of a poor Louſy Souldier or two for Robbing, is redreſs and Satisfaction enough for their own Crimes, and thoſe of their Officers; but I would adviſe the Fellow to go down to <hi>Hounſlow,</hi> and the parts adjacent, or into the Countreys where they quarter, and inquire there, and no doubt but he will hear of many Abuſes and Wrongs done that are yet unſatisfied, even <hi>Rapes</hi> and <hi>Murders.</hi> But perhaps <hi>Jack</hi> may be in the right of it too: for the <hi>Soldiers</hi> have done no man an injury in his ſence, that is, no <hi>Papiſt;</hi> for in his opinion the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are but like <hi>Caterpillars</hi> and <hi>Vermin,</hi> that ſtands in the <hi>good Catholicks</hi> way, and ought to be knocked on the Head, and ſent out of the world, and therefore it is no injury to <hi>Rob</hi> and <hi>Murder</hi> them.</p>
            <p>In Page 29. he makes a great Noiſe about the <hi>King's Nativity,</hi> and ſays, I have calculated it, for which he doth not a little Abuſe me with his <hi>unmannerly Billingsgate Complements,</hi> and ſays alſo, that I have predicted the <hi>King's Death.</hi> Yet after all, he tells the world, that the <hi>King's Nativity</hi> is not known. Why, is not this next door to <hi>Nonſenſe?</hi> For me to do a Nativity that is not known. But if it be known, or believed to be ſo, the <hi>King</hi> is the leſs beholding to that <hi>ſcandalous Fellow Gadbury,</hi> who printed it the year 1659.— But he gives us one ſpecial Reaſon (and he ſays, that muſt ſerve for all) why the Nativity he printed was not the <hi>Kings</hi> true one, and that is, <hi>No Imperial Nativity can have the Moon in the twelfth Houſe.</hi> Now how far he would ſtrain the word <hi>Imperial</hi> I know not. I ſuppoſe he means not leſs than a <hi>Crowned Head,</hi> and in that ſence I will take it. <hi>Now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</hi> if you look into the <hi>Collection of Genitures,</hi> printed by Mr. <hi>J. Gadbury,</hi> pag. 23. there you ſhall find that <hi>Henry the ſecond, King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> had both <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> in the <hi>twelfth Houſe:</hi> and in Page 52. of the ſame Book, you will find the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Denmark</hi> hath his <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>twelfth Houſe;</hi> and both theſe printed and publiſhed by that <hi>ignorant</hi> but great <hi>Impoſtor</hi> J. G. Now whether he forgot theſe, or impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſerted this to out-face the matter to make his <hi>Maſter</hi> believe, that what he hath writ is true: I will leave to his own Confeſſion, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107620:11"/>conclude, that a Lyar ought to have a good memory, the want of which is it ſeems this poor Gentlemans misfortune: for theſe were both <hi>Imperial Nativities,</hi> and both <hi>Crowned Heads.</hi> Of which I could give you more Examples were it convenient: but two out of his own Book is more than ten out of the moſt Authentick Author in being, and proves the Fellows Impudence the greater.</p>
            <p>In Page 30. he baſely abuſeth me, when he ſays, that I doom'd the <hi>French King to Death</hi> three years ago, <hi>which is falſe:</hi> for I never had any Diſcourſe with <hi>him</hi> in <hi>three years</hi> before that, except September the <hi>9th</hi> 1685. and then we had no diſcourſe of that nature. So that I perceive he had it by hear-ſay, or elſe he made it to ſerve the turn at this time; but be it how it will, I ſuppoſe there is an ingenious <hi>Gentleman,</hi> living near <hi>Ludgate,</hi> that can <hi>juſtifie</hi> me in this that I ſhall now ſay, and he underſtands <hi>Aſtrology</hi> well, Mr. C. B. who is the <hi>Gentleman</hi> I mentioned before, met me in <hi>March</hi> or <hi>April,</hi> 1685. in an evening between <hi>Lydgate</hi> and St. <hi>Pau's.</hi> And after other Diſcourſe about <hi>Nativities,</hi> he asked me, if the <hi>King of France</hi> would dye that year; and if I had ever ſaid ſo, I told him, that he had two very <hi>bad Directions</hi> then coming up, but I durſt not be poſitive concerning his Death; but I did believe if he did not dye, yet he would very narrowly eſcape it; but I had never ſaid poſitively, that he would dye. And in this thing, that <hi>Gentleman</hi> if he pleaſeth, can do me Juſtice, till I can come to do my ſelf Juſtice upon this <hi>Lying pittiful Fellow.</hi> Now let any man that obſerved that year, and the <hi>French King's</hi> Affairs, remember in what condition he was between <hi>October</hi> that year, and <hi>April</hi> or <hi>May</hi> the year following, when he lay in that wretched fulſom Condition, that as the Letters gave us an account, he ſtunk, and was noiſome to his Attendants, by reaſon of that Diſtemper in <hi>Ano,</hi> yet it held him about a year and more: but the greateſt danger was in the firſt <hi>ſix Months.</hi> Now the reaſon why I could not be poſitive, whether he would live or dye, was from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections he then had to operate, that I had not had Experience of, neither doth <hi>Gadbury</hi> know any thing of it to this day.</p>
            <p>But I remember a certain <hi>Gentleman</hi> that I could name, went to <hi>Gadbury</hi> after the late <hi>King</hi> dyed and asked him, upon what direction he Aſtrologically dyed? and with a great deal of ſop-gravity he told him, <hi>that it was the Phyſicians:</hi> chereby intimating that the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> had <hi>murdered</hi> him; which was very diſingenious of him to blame thoſe <hi>Gentleman</hi> that uſed their utmoſt endeavour to preſerve him; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he could give no true account of his death Aſtrologically, nor really any at all, tho he dyed upon the operation of ſix or ſeven Directions, and therefore he was obliged to make uſe of any Sham to ſtop the <hi>Gentlemans mouth</hi> that asked him.</p>
            <p>In Page 32. he ſhews his Skill in Aſtrology: where he denies that the <hi>part of Fortune</hi> can be directed for l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e. Pray Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi> what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107620:11"/>
               <hi>kill'd Charles the firſt of England?</hi> I know your Anſwer; for you can make no other but this, that he ſuffered upon the <hi>Direction</hi> of the <hi>Aſcendent</hi> to the <hi>Square of Mars;</hi> if ſo, why did not the <hi>Aſcendent</hi> to the <hi>Square</hi> of <hi>Mars</hi> kill in the <hi>Earl of Eſſex his Nativity? Like Cauſes, like Effects:</hi> for none of your Shams ſhall paſs upon me: can you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve this point now with all your Skill? And in the <hi>Earl of Strafford's Nativity,</hi> you make the <hi>Midheaven</hi> to the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> kill: and the <hi>Sun is giver of Life.</hi> Yet in the Nativity of the <hi>Princeſs Royal:</hi> the <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heaven</hi> to the <hi>body if Mars</hi> gives <hi>Marriage:</hi> is not this fine Stuff? And in the Caſe of <hi>Henry the Eighth,</hi> and <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> neither the <hi>body</hi> nor the <hi>oppoſition</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> would kill: are not you aſhamed of this Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? if you are not, you may. But I ſhall <hi>expoſe you</hi> and your <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection</hi> in a treatiſe by it ſelf, in which Caſe I will uſe you very kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but in the mean time pray tell us fairly in print what Direction it was that <hi>kill'd</hi> that <hi>worthy Gentleman</hi> Sr. <hi>Frech. Hollis:</hi> He that you promiſed him, he ſhould live ſome <hi>decades of years,</hi> and he was ſhot to pieces within <hi>fix Months</hi> after. Juſt ſo, you will cheat the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and your <hi>Maſter</hi> too; for <hi>the part of Fortune</hi> is <hi>Hileg</hi> in his <hi>Nativity,</hi> and ſo it was in his <hi>Fathers.</hi> Pray tell us, by what <hi>Rules</hi> in <hi>Aſtrology</hi> you predicted the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be brought to bed of a <hi>Boy</hi> in the year 1686. Did not the Devil and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> deceive you that bout? I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it was a <hi>Whitehal Scheam</hi> which you judged that by, perhaps of the ſame mans ſetting as that was which you predicted the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the City of <hi>Londons</hi> Charter by, though you laid the ſham on an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe</hi> of the <hi>Moon</hi> you know. Now when you have conſidered all this <hi>Nonſenſe, Sham</hi> and <hi>Cheat,</hi> how can you have the impudence to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be Maſter and Teacher of any other Aſtrology than a falſe one? and who do you think will believe you, Fools excepted?</p>
            <p>Likewiſe in the ſame Page 32. he is ſo notoriouſly bold as to deny my quotations from <hi>Ptolomey,</hi> that is lib. 3. Chap. 12. <hi>de parte Fortunae,</hi> and Chap. 13. <hi>Quot ſint Prorogatores.</hi> The firſt of which he ſays treats of <hi>de Impedimentis &amp; Infirmitatibus Nati,</hi> &amp;c. and the ſecond <hi>de qualitatibus Animae Nati.</hi> Now I will appeal to all thoſe Gentlemen that have that worthy Author by them of the beſt Impreſſion, which is that of <hi>Melancthon,</hi> who is in the truth He or I; for if the 12. and 13. <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of the <hi>third Book</hi> of <hi>Ptolomeys Quadripartite</hi> doth not treat the one <hi>departe Fortunae,</hi> and the other <hi>de Prorogatoribus;</hi> then I never have read that Book in my whole life: But I ſuppoſe this Fellow hath cheared himſelf with the Tranſlation of <hi>Camerarius,</hi> which is the worſt in being, but it is indeed good enough for him; for if he had a better, he knows not what uſe to make of it. Now you that are able to examine this Caſe and judge it, will ſee what a <hi>ſtrange Fellow</hi> I have here to do with; for the <hi>two Chapters</hi> he there alledgeth are the 17. and the 18. of that <hi>third Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Page 33. he tells us, that he was there about to lay by his pen:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107620:12"/>but upon new Conſiderations freſh Matter came in, and my preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rications and abuſe of art makes him enter into a long preamble a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Conjunctions of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> of which he gives you a very lame account, but it ſerves to thoſe that do not underſtand bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but to what purpoſe he luggs them in I know not, neither can I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend any occaſion for them in his pretended anſwer to that Alman.</p>
            <p>In Page 40. he brings in the <hi>Palladium of Rome,</hi> to ſhew you that it is under no ſuch misfortunes as I pretend to ſay it is, neither ſays he, is there any reaſon for it, in the figure he produceth: in the firſt place, I never ſpoke any thing as to the <hi>Buildings</hi> and <hi>Foundations</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> but the Cheating <hi>Crew</hi> that there reſides; for it is not againſt the <hi>ſtone Walls</hi> that I ſhoot, but the <hi>Murder, Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Villany</hi> of thoſe that pretend to be the <hi>Head, Members</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> of that <hi>curſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Society,</hi> who <hi>prophanely</hi> call themſelves the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> for in the ſame Houſes there might good pious People dwell, were theſe removed or deſtroyed: and <hi>Rome</hi> may be <hi>Rome,</hi> when the <hi>Pope</hi> and all his <hi>Lewd Buggering Clergy</hi> are gone: But if <hi>Gadbury</hi> pleaſeth to conſider the preſent Affairs between the <hi>King of France</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> and how dreadfully that Storm threatens the <hi>Holy See</hi> if it goes forward, I ſuppoſe he will not be ſo impertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſitive in his Judgment from the <hi>Palladium</hi> now, as he was at the writing of that <hi>Malicious Pamphlet.</hi> Again, let him with this alſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how the <hi>Lords Inquiſitors</hi> and <hi>Cardinals</hi> did handle the <hi>Pope</hi> in the Affairs of <hi>Molinos.</hi> I think this is an untoward <hi>Omen</hi> to the <hi>Grandeur</hi> of the <hi>Infallible Power</hi> lodged in the <hi>Pope,</hi> as they ſay. Which is further aggravated by that ſlight they put upon his <hi>Bull</hi> at <hi>Colien;</hi> all which conſidered together, tells us, that either the <hi>Palladium</hi> is a falſe poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or elſe the <hi>Prophetical Interpreter</hi> thereof gives a <hi>Lying Judgment</hi> to delude the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Rome stands, 'tis true, unable to defie</l>
               <l>One Monarch's Fury, or our Propheſy.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>In Page 42. the Fellow tells us, that the Heavens ſhew glorious things not only to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> but to all <hi>Christcadom,</hi> to the advancement of the <hi>true Religion,</hi> and the depreſſion of <hi>Hereſy</hi> and <hi>Schiſm.</hi> This Hereſy that he here ſpeaks of, is the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> which you ſee he hath here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to deſtruction and ruin for which they are infinitely obliged to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and the <hi>true Religion</hi> to be advanced and eſtabliſhed, is <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> in which this Fellow is imbarked.</p>
            <p>In Page 46. he ſays, <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was fetcht out of priſon by a <hi>kind-hearted old Woman:</hi> which was Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> the pillory'd <hi>Popiſh Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife.</hi> Well <hi>Jack,</hi> did She releaſe him from thence for pure Charity's ſake or not? No: he was to be her <hi>Stallion,</hi> to kill the <hi>King,</hi> and to get in her <hi>Husband's Debts</hi> Nay then I think he was to earn his Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and She knowing that he had been whip'd and pillory'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107620:12"/>as you ſay He was, gave Her aſſurance enough, that He was fit for the deſign She releaſed him for: People of an equal Share of <hi>Sence,</hi> of <hi>Reputation</hi> or <hi>Honesty</hi> always delight in each others Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; Like the Proverb, <hi>Similis ſimili gaudet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He goes on and tells us, that I have bounded the Happineſs of <hi>England;</hi> and that it ſhall terminate in <hi>October</hi> 1688. but this is falſe. For I conclude, that the Glory and Happineſs of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> and <hi>Church of England,</hi> will then begin to appear, and ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after thrive and flouriſh again, to the Eternal ſorrow and grief of <hi>Jack Gadbury,</hi> and all his <hi>curſed Faction,</hi> that ſo much deſire and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the ruin and deſtruction of the <hi>Protestants,</hi> and <hi>Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> But like a Fool He tells the World there, that I threaten the <hi>King</hi> with <hi>Poyſon,</hi> when I mention the <hi>Spaniſh Apple.</hi> I perceive the Fellow is Ignorant what the meaning of an <hi>Orangien Apple</hi> is; and if he be, let him be ſo ſtill, till the Judgment of God comes upon them.</p>
            <p>And at laſt, he hits on the great Myſtery, and tells us, that <hi>I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got my ſelf, and fooliſhly talk of things to happen ſeveral years after we are all destroyed.</hi> Now who He means by the word <hi>we,</hi> I cannot perfectly tell. I ſuppoſe he means the <hi>Papists;</hi> for he cannot be ſo impudent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all theſe <hi>villanies</hi> and <hi>abuſive Language</hi> to the <hi>Church of England</hi> and <hi>Protestants,</hi> crying up <hi>Popery,</hi> and railing at its Enemies, calling them <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Rebels,</hi> &amp;c. to believe any man will think him a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant</hi> tho he ſays he is, or to ſhroud himſelf under that title for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. For in his Station and to the beſt of his power, he hath been as ill a man as any among them, no diſparagement to others. But if he means <hi>we Papists,</hi> I do not doubt of ſeeing them deſtroyed either in <hi>perſon</hi> or <hi>power,</hi> or <hi>both;</hi> and this in a ſhorter time than the man thinks of; and after that, to ſee thoſe other Effects of the <hi>conjunction</hi> that will happen in thoſe <hi>years,</hi> that doth ſucceed the time of their <hi>oppoſition,</hi> which like the <hi>conjunction</hi> is a triple one, and are in the year 1692. and 1693. from <hi>Sagitary</hi> and <hi>Gemini,</hi> and doth particularly concern <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>The CONCLUSION.</head>
            <p>NOw by way of Concluſion: I will firſt be ſo kind to Mr. <hi>J. Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> as to give him half a dozen Aſtrological operations in his own Nativity, which he is not able to perform himſelf. And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I will give him ſome good advice, fit for one that is under ſuch <hi>times</hi> and <hi>circumstances</hi> as he himſelf is, which I hope will reform him.</p>
            <p>Since his coming out of the <hi>Gatehouſe priſon,</hi> in the year 1679. he hath had ſeveral eminent directions, the chief of which were the <hi>mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en</hi> to the <hi>mine</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Venus;</hi> but now the caſe is altered; and he hath in the years following ſome of a contrary nature and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ect to operate, as you may here ſee:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107620:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Moon ad quad: Mercur: mdo dd:</cell>
                     <cell>Arcus:</cell>
                     <cell>60 : 48</cell>
                     <cell>61 ye: 2 mon.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Aſcend ad Corp: Jovis —</cell>
                     <cell>Arc:</cell>
                     <cell>61 : 48</cell>
                     <cell>62 ye: 2 mon.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sol ad par: Satur: in Zodiaco</cell>
                     <cell>Arc:</cell>
                     <cell>64 : 3</cell>
                     <cell>64 ye: 10 mon.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Luna ad quadr. Solis mdo dd:</cell>
                     <cell>Arc:</cell>
                     <cell>65 : 31</cell>
                     <cell>66 ye: 4 mon.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Luna ad par: Martis motu rapto:</cell>
                     <cell>Arc:</cell>
                     <cell>65 : 56</cell>
                     <cell>66 ye: 9 mon.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sol ad oppoſiti Saturni —</cell>
                     <cell>Arc:</cell>
                     <cell>68 : 57</cell>
                     <cell>70 ye: 2 mon.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>The Aſcendent to the body of <hi>Jupiter</hi> is a good direction, but it is ſo attended, that it will loſe much of its Luſtre; for beſides thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after it, in that very year the Moon comes to the body of <hi>Mars,</hi> Square of <hi>Mercury,</hi> and Square of the <hi>Sun,</hi> all Secundary; and therefore it cannot be ſo great as it would have been otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>But for the four laſt directions here mentioned, I muſt tell him that they will put all his <hi>Popiſh Politicks,</hi> and <hi>pious ver tues</hi> into exerciſe; and it will be well, if he keeps out of his old <hi>Lodging</hi> at the entrance into the <hi>Palace yard</hi> again. And yet I dare aſſure him, that none of theſe directions will kill him, they only give trouble or travel.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing the Stars will be ſo <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>unkind</hi> to their <hi>great</hi> and <hi>only Secretary</hi> and <hi>Minion</hi> Dr. <hi>Jack,</hi> I would adviſe him to lead a <hi>godly, righteous</hi> and <hi>ſober life,</hi> (which he never did yet) and by that means prepare himſelf to undergo and receive the fury of theſe angry Stars. The beſt way I can adviſe him, is to run over <hi>his beads</hi> twice a day more than ordinary, <hi>whip himſelf</hi> harder and more on <hi>good Fryday,</hi> hear <hi>Maſs</hi> frequently, and go as often as may be to Father <hi>Peters</hi> to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion;</hi> and this being done, there is no doubt of his being a Saint, and as good a Chriſtian as Pope <hi>John</hi> the twelfth, <hi>Raviliack,</hi> or <hi>Guido Vaux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And my friend being come to this pitch of piety, fit to receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, I would adviſe him to repent of all his villanies againſt the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Subjects of England,</hi> in raving to have the <hi>Test</hi> repealed, in which caſe I do recommend to his conſideration the Letter of the <hi>Penſimaris Fagel,</hi> where he is aſſured, that the <hi>true Heir</hi> to the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is really againſt ſetting up <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Repealing</hi> the <hi>Test;</hi> which I hope every true <hi>Engliſhman</hi> will take notice of: and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe <hi>one and twenty moneths is not an age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His ſhaming the <hi>fire of London;</hi> for which let him read Sir <hi>Robert Brooks</hi>'s report to the Committee.</p>
            <p>His Juſtifying the <hi>murder</hi> of the <hi>Protestants</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> and denying that the <hi>Papists</hi> murdered Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> with many more: which I hope ſo religious a man as this is will lay to heart, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily repent of.</p>
            <p>When thou ſaweſt a <hi>thief</hi> thou conſentedſt with him, and haſt been <hi>partakers</hi> with <hi>Adulterers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things thou haſt done, and I kept ſilence; thou thoughteſt that I was altogether ſuch a one as <hi>thy ſelf,</hi> Pſalm 50.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>oppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Saturn</hi> in the ſame Aſpect with the Sun. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Knave</hi> and <hi>Treader,</hi> Collec: Genitu: Aph. 87.</p>
            <p>This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was made by <hi>J. Gadbury,</hi> and it takes place in his own Nativity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107620:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
